ABDEL-MAGID MROUEH

Beirut, Lebanon | P: +9613156008 | magidmroueh@gmail.com | <u>LinkedIn</u> | <u>GitHub</u> Languages: Arabic, English, French

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A software engineer with experience leading teams with more than 6 local and remote developers. Delivered different known products in Lebanon and the region like Onlivery (Lebanon), FinTech: ZainCash agent app/dashboard - Fintech (Iraq), Blu Loyalty (Lebanon and GCC), essmak.com and Quest Education E-commerce website and learning system (Lebanon). Also worked on a microservices based point of sale system and e-commerce website for G-group (Lebanon). Experience working using multiple technologies on both backend (PHP, Node.js) and frontend (react, angular, typescript) with the willingness to learn new stacks and technologies.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Toothpick and Markit apps, Beirut — Senior Software Engineer sep 2020 - Present

- Led the communication and integrated the existing application with third party providers for online payments and logistics.
- Improved and set new rules for the git flow.
- Introduced new practices for the web development team to improve the code quality.
- Upgraded all the frameworks to latest stable versions, and managed the compatibility of the systems with latest php and node versions.
- Mentored junior developers.

Postlight, New York (Remote-Beirut) — Senior Software Engineer Aug 2019 - Sep 2020

- Delivered 3 News websites based on wordpress multi-site architecture (CopperCourier, Courier, UpNorth).
- Deployed multiple features on Dash slack plugin.
- Led the development and delivered the new Poslight.com website, applying new designs and functionalities then deployed using CircleCI to wordpress VIP servers.
- Provided maintenance and support for multiple in-house open source projects (headless wordpress and react starter, TinySheet, TinyMonth).
- Staffed as a team augmentation senior engineer on the SageSure client on their Agent Portal project built with React.js and tested with react-testing-library based on Jest.
- Mentored junior developers and Led technical conversations with clients.
- Identified and solved technical debt and risks in projects.

IdeaToLife, Beirut — Technical Lead May 2017 - Jul 2019

- Led the projects life-cycle from architecture to execution.
- Participated in the design thinking sessions and oversaw the design of applications from functional and technical specifications.
- Led the architecture of a microservices based ERP and E-commerce for G-Group.
- Interviewed, hired and mentored senior and junior developers in Lebanon and abroad.
- Enforced the use of latest technologies in PHP and node.js, and the use of modern frameworks Laravel/Lumen, Express.js for backEnd and Angular 6 for frontEnd.
- Applied TDD and functional programming processes and unit tested our code.
- Led the development and delivery of SkinSociety.me, essmak.com, Quest Education,
 ZainCash and other projects.
- Refactored and rewritten the backend of Onlivery food delivery application.

Blu Solutions, Beirut — Senior Software Engineer Jun 2015 - May 2017

- Designed, developed and maintained applications using Laravel and CodeIgniter.
- Made recommendations and developed technical design for new application features.
- Identified and corrected performance issues and Prepared detailed technical design specifications for Software.
- Implemented new services into production,
- Ensured proper release and maintenance of all systems.

Layout Intl., Beirut — *Software Engineer* Jan 2014 - Jun 2015

- Developed and maintained a Newspaper workflow system and an archiving system using pure PHP and MySQL technologies.
- Participated in the development of an online CMS for websites using Zend framework.
- Participated in the development of new websites.
- Led the full lifecycle of the central intelligence room (CIR) product.

Link Systems, Kuwait — *Software Engineer (Contract)* Jun 2013 - Dec 2013

- Led the development and delivery of Venus HRS, an employee time attendance and HR system integrated with physical fingerprint machines built with PHP and MsSQL server.
- Participated in the Design, Development and requirement collection and Restructured the DataBase of an old system.
- Trained users in the proper use of the system.
- Participated in the hiring and training of fresh grad developers.

ClearTag, Beirut — Web Developer Mar 2013 - May 2013

- Provided maintenance of existing projects. IPT, MTN, Audi cards, Audi rewards and Rymco Using YII PHP framework.

Layout LTD, Beirut — Software Engineer Aug 2012 - Feb 2013

- Participated in the development of Precisa, a printing cost. estimation software built with PHP and MySQL.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science: Computer Science, 2012 Lebanese International University - Beirut, Lebanon

SKILLS

PHP (Laravel, Lumen), Node.js, socket.io, Angular, React.js, Jest, Express, CI/CD, TDD, DDD, Database (MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDb), GraphQL, Elastic Search, MVC, Git version control system, SOAP & REST web services.

CERTIFICATES

- Introduction to CyberSecurity, CISCO, 2020.
- JavaScript algorithms and Data Structure, FreeCodeCamp, 2019.
- Responsive Web Design, FreeCodeCamp, 2019.
- Managing Big Data with MySQL, Coursera, 2016.